Matthew T. Bowen

Profile

Matt is a highly motivated graduate of Queen's University with a Honours Bachelor's Degree in Physics and Computing. A technical mind and charismatic demeanor combine with excellent problem solving and communication skills. Matt derives knowledge and experience from three major avenues; academic, hobbyist, and professional: strong knowledge of computational methods applied to physics and software development, experienced in amateur electrical engineering in photovoltaics and space systems, and a professional team leader and decision-maker.

Education

Queen's University

Kingston, ON

Bachelor of Science (Honours - Physics Major, Computing Minor)

2013 - 2018

- Dean's Honour List recipient: 2013-2016

Experience

Alma Mater Society of Queen's University Inc

Kingston, ON

Director of Information Technology

March 2017 - Present

- Full time salaried position amongst the AMS Senior Directors, responsible for corporation-wide decision making and strategic planning.
- Maintains the technological infrastructure, performs account management, and oversees project development for the AMS
- Manages, trains and advises staff in their capacity as first level support to the AMS.

Queen's Space Engineering Team - Satellite Project

Kingston, ON

' Electrical Head

May 2017 - Present

- Designs and implements the power generation and delivery system for CoSMOSat.
- Manages the periphery electrical subsystems, including command/data-handling, and attitude determination.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON

Electrical Projects Director

May 2016 - April 2017

- Member of QSDT Executive Directors, and was responsible for sole decision making on all electrical matters
- Oversaw the electrical sub-team of QSDT. Delegated and monitored projects in data collection, energy storage, and low power home electricity usage.
- Designed and installed a fully off-grid photovoltaic power generation system for a 600sqft home.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON

Data Systems Manager

September 2015 - April 2016

- Designed and installed weather and data monitoring systems for the Queen's Solar Education Centre.
- Includes hardware implementation throughout the home as well as software development.

Arts & Science Undergraduate Society

Kingston, ON

Peer Tutor

September 2015 - Present

- Provides academic assistance for fellow students, as well as foster beneficial habits and skills in the tutee.

Queen's Athletics and Recreation

Kingston, ON

Intramural Official - Basketball

September 2014 - March 2018

- Ensured the safety and inclusiveness of participants, and upheld the regulations of intramural activities.

School District #71 of British Columbia

Courtenay, BC

Groundskeeper and Delivery Driver

May 2015 - September 2015

 Maintained the infrastructure of schools, and engaged in new projects to enhance the teaching and recreational spaces at those schools. Compiled, loaded, and delivered equipment orders for school events.

Domo Japan Restaurant

Courtenay, BC

Line Cook May 2014 - September 2014

 Processed customer orders quickly and efficiently in keeping with the high standards of food presentation, quality, and timeliness that are upheld at Domo Japan.

Skills Profile

Platforms: C, Java, Python (most proficient), MATLAB, HTML/CSS/PHP/JavaScript, LaTeX

Operating Systems: Windows 98/XP/Vista/7/8.1/10, Unix/Linux

Tools: Mathematica, MatLab, AGI Systems Tool Kit, SQL Server, MS Office, git, GIMP/InDesign/Visio, TRNSYS

Scientific and Mathematical: Differential and discrete mathematics and vector calculus. Scientific statistics. Knowledge of computational methods for physics and engineering. Modern physics theory.

Hardware: Knowledge of photovoltaic systems, including design and installation. Familiar with Campbell Scientific data acquisition systems. Experience with electronic lab equipment, circuit design, and usage of Arduino/RPi microprocessors. Amateur woodworker and automobile mechanic.

Projects

NGVS Surface Brightness Profile Fitting

Kingston, ON

Honours Physics Thesis Project

September 2017 - May 2018

- Study the light profile of Virgo Cluster galaxies to detect the trace of stellar halos
- Use of chi-squared and Markov Chain Monte Carlo minimization techniques to determine the light percentage contributed by halo stars

Investigating Hydrodynamic Quantum Analogues

Kingston, ON

Physics Laboratory, PHYS 350

December 2016 - May 2017

- By mechanically vibrating viscous fluids, several quantum mechanical effects can be demonstrated.

Implementing a Kalman Filter for Apogee Detection in Atmospheric Rocket Flight

Kingston, ON

Queen's Rocket Engineering Team

September 2016 - January 2017

- Research into the viability of using a Kalman filter to deploy airbrakes on atmospheric rocket flight
- Implementation of algorithm using an Arduino platform with pressure altimeter and 9-axis accelerometer

Determining the Width of the Kirkwood Gaps

Kingston, ON

Computational Methods in Physics, PHYS 313

September 2015 - December 2015

- Wrote a limited N-body code (in C) to simulate the motion of asteroids in resonance with Jupiter and Saturn
- Co-wrote scientific report detailing the findings and results of the Verlet simulation

Certifications and Memberships

•	Working at Heights The Safety Guys	Kingston, ON June 2016
•	CPR-C First Aid Canadian Red Cross	Belleville, ON <i>April 2015</i>
•	Amateur Radio Operator (callsign: VE3KSP) Innovation, Science, and Economic Development Canada	Toronto, ON February 2017
•	Workplace Hazardous Materials Information System Queen's University	Kingston, ON <i>May 2016</i>
•	Sexual Violence Bystander Intervention training Queen's University	Kingston, ON <i>May 2017</i>